Good morning today is the 28th of תמוז Tammuz we're on נ"ב
עמוד א' Nun Bais Amud Aleph but starting with the משנה Mishna
on the bottom of נ"א עמוד ב' Nun Aleph Amud Bais we
apologize for the fact that there is no video because the computer
is not here and my name is Dan Margulies I'm filling in
for Rabbi Linszer while he is on vacation.
So the משנה Mishna says: הנודר מן החלב Ha-noder min ha-chalav if
a person takes a נדר neder not to get any benefit from
milk מותר בקום muttar b'kum it's permissible for him to get benefit
from whey. Whey is the liquid that's produced during cheese making yogurt
making different kinds of curdling processes that separates the protein solids from
the liquid of the milk so the קום kum the whey of
the milk would separate out it's not included in the נדר neder
against חלב. chalav. רבי יוסי אוסר Rabbi Yose oser even though it's
still dairy.
So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose forbids we're going to see that the
way our גמרא Gemara the בבלי Bavli understands this משנה Mishna is
not about whether or not technically whey really falls into the category
of milk or not but really is לשון בני אדם. Lashon bnei
adam. Like we've been seeing before throughout by נדרים Nedarim we really
only care about לשון בני אדם Lashon bnei adam so many of
these points which could be a technical מחלוקת machlokes about how to
classify different foods will end up being a bit more how to
say
superficial however the ירושלמי Yerushalmi actually seems to note that this is
a real מחלוקת machlokes between תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and רבי יוסי
Rabbi Yose about the nature of the whey whether it really counts
as milk or not. Again when what our משנה Mishna at least
when a person says I'm having milk it doesn't mean I'm having
מילכיק milchik so that's an interesting point as well. Okay so
רבי יוסי אוסר. Rabbi Yose oser. מן הקום Min ha-kum what if
a person takes a נדר neder against whey מותר בחלב muttar b'chalav
even תנא קמא Tanna Kamma will admit that whey is more specific
than milk and for sure if you take a נדר neder against
whey you do not mean to forbid milk to yourself. It's also
interesting to note because of that that the process by which milk
is turned into curds and whey is a process that produces two
new foods because otherwise you would say oh the milk is just
a mixture of curds and whey together and whenever you would drink
milk it would have whey in it anyway and therefore when you
take a נדר neder against קום kum you are eating milk itself
sorry when you take a נדר neder against the קום kum the
whey then even drinking milk you are consuming whey. So the fact
is no this משנה Mishna notes the fact that whey is a
new substance produced during the curdling of the milk. Interesting to note
as well the גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbos makes clear that cheese
making process the curdling process מחבץ mechabetz is a problem because of
בורר borer separating between two different items that are in a mixture.
בונה Boneh is מגבץ megabbetz the cheese making that's taking the curds
and pressing them together. But the curdling process is an earlier step
מחבץ mechabetz and מחבץ mechabetz is called תולדה toladah of בורר borer
it's a derivative מלאכה melacha of the מלאכה melacha of בורר borer
separating between a mixture. So from the גמרא Gemara in שבת Shabbos
it sounds like the way הלכה halacha thinks of milk is that
milk really is a mixture of cheese solids and whey together and
this משנה Mishna seems to hold otherwise. So it's just an interesting
point how would we reconcile those two points I don't have a
good answer for it now but I think it's an interesting question.
Okay so person takes נדר מן הקום מותר בחלב neder min ha-kum
muttar b'chalav אבא שאול Abba Shaul and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose and
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma would agree מותר בחלב. muttar b'chalav. אבא
שאול אומר: Abba Shaul Omer: הנודר מן הגבינה אסור בה בין מלוחה
וטפלה. Ha-noder min ha-gevina asur bah bein melucha u'tefeila. אבא שאול Abba
Shaul says
if a person takes a נדר neder not to eat cheese it's
forbidden to eat either salted cheese or unsalted cheese.
Why would you think otherwise?
Why would you think otherwise? Perhaps because the most common kind of
cheese is a cheese that has salt so I would think only
the salted cheese but no even people call unsalted cheese cheese.
I feel like I'm missing something because I mean you can eat
crackers with unsalted or salted.
Well again in our culture we would think of both of those
as cheese. Perhaps that was more of a conceptual stretch for the
תנאים Tannaim to think of an unsalted cheese as really qualifying as
a cheese for them it was more of a stretch to say
that
but nonetheless they're willing to say yes that does fall into the
category of cheese. We note also we saw with examples from before
and they're coming up later different types of meat or different preparation
methods of meat would fall under different kinds of words. So maybe
that the word גבינה gevina really did mean a salted cheese and
nonetheless even the unsalted cheese qualifies as well there's no other good
word for cheese besides גבינה gevina at least. So again different possibilities
I don't know enough about the realia to tell you about the
cheese eating culture of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael in the second century
to tell you broader context of this משנה. Mishna. I'll keep going
הנודר מן הבשר Ha-noder min ha-basar if a person takes a נדר
neder not to eat meat מותר ברוטב muttar b'rotev it is permitted
to eat the gravy. ובקיפה u'v'kippah and the cracklings or something. וכיפה
v'kippah I think is the dregs, right? It's something what the מפרש
mefarish says ובקיפה u'v'kippah מקיפה הוה מתבלין mi-kippa ava mitavlin פונדלריש pundelerish
בלעז. b'la'az. So he says it's the thick, a kind of like
a thick paste of the spices or something. It's something that drips
to the bottom of the pan when it's being prepared perhaps.
Some kind of cracklings or drippings from the meat preparation. So the
רוטב rotev is some kind of gravy that has a meat flavor,
it has bits of meat in it perhaps, but is not a
piece of meat. So because you took a נדר neder not to
eat meat, you meant to make, you meant to say a piece
of meat, a steak, a chicken leg, and not the gravy or
the little bits and pieces here and there that are floating around.
This is going to be, you know, you see this gigantic ר"ן
Ran here, so this becomes the מחלוקת machloket between רש"י Rashi and
the ר"ן, Ran, which maybe we'll touch on a little bit later
about דבר שיש לו מתירים davar she-yesh lo matirin and ביטול bittul
and מין במינו min b'mino and מין בשאינו מינו. min b'she'eino mino.
Okay, רבי יוסי אוסר. Rabbi Yosi oser. So רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi
would forbid those because רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi says fine, even the
gravy counts as meat because it has little bits of meat, it
has the taste of the meat. Okay.
אמר רבי יהודה. Amar Rabbi Yehuda. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda אוסר
oser and now we have אמר רבי יהודה amar Rabbi Yehuda a
new clause because it says אמר, amar, but it may be that
this story supports his position because he says מעשה ואסר עלינו רבי
טרפון בביצים שנתבשלו עמו. Ma'aseh v'asar aleinu Rabbi Tarfon b'veitzim shenitbashlu imo.
There was a case that this happened, someone, meaning someone or many,
several people at this meal had taken a נדר neder not to
eat meat. Interesting we talk about vegetarians today, is a person who
announces publicly many times in public that they're keeping a vegetarian diet
or a vegan diet, does that really qualify as a נדר neder
הלכתית halachitit to the extent that the person would have to worry
about it if they would ever decide to stop keeping that diet
is an interesting question.
So I'll leave it at that. But so רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
said that they would not be allowed to eat, he forbade them
to eat the eggs which were cooked with the meat.
Like the cholent.
So this is like a Sephardi cholent or different kinds of things
where the eggs have cooked with the meat. The egg has absorbed
presumably the flavor of the meat and therefore, and רבי טרפון Rabbi
Tarfon was מחמיר machmir that even an egg cooked in a meat
stew qualifies as meat for the purpose of נדרים. nedarim. If a
person took a נדר neder not to eat meat, even the egg
cooked in the meat would be forbidden. And that's a proof for
רבי יהודה's Rabbi Yehuda position that
even therefore obviously the gravy and the וכיפה, v'kippah, whatever the וכיפה
v'kippah is, cracklings or something, that those would be forbidden as well.
אמרו לו, Amru lo, כן הדבר. kein hadavar. So they said fine,
that was the case. אבל אימתי, Aval eimatai, under what circumstances? בזמן
שיאמר בשר זה עלי. Bizman she-yomar basar zeh alay. So if a
person says this meat will be forbidden to me, שהנודר מן הדבר
ונתערב באחר אם יש בו בנותן טעם אסור. she-hanoder min hadavar v'nitarev
b'acher im yesh bo b'noten ta'am asur.
So because if a person took a נדר neder from one thing
and then it mixed with something else, meaning I took a נדר
neder from meat and meat then mixed with egg, ah, then it
only, it only would apply אם יש בו בנותן טעם im yesh
bo b'noten ta'am if there is a בנותן טעם. b'noten ta'am. If
the meat gave a flavor to the egg and the הלכתי halachic
טעם, ta'am, again this gets into major questions of כשרות, kashrut, but
this is a big source for the point that we rely on
טעם. ta'am. So the fact that טעם ta'am is important, we could
say טעם כעיקר, ta'am k'ikar, the flavor is, we follow the flavor
in terms of ביטול bittul and things like that, and that it's
even if it's secondary, etc., etc., so אסור. asur.
And again this gets into a
נדרים nedarim question as opposed to... well, but even any question of
כשרות kashrut is boiling down eventually to a question of איסור והיתר.
issur v'heter. Any kind of meat and milk together is אסור בהנאה
asur b'hana'ah in some sense. Non-kosher meat is not אסור בהנאה asur
b'hana'ah but it's אסור באכילה, asur b'achilah, and there's a lot of
לומדות lomdus about that. But
so this is getting into still the question if I have something
which I took a נדר neder again and then it mixed in,
right, we discussed this the other day about the coins. If a
person was נודר noder from however, you know, my, my sack of
coins is אסור asur to you and now he goes and buys
things in the marketplace, would that mean that therefore every coin will
be אסור? asur? So no, we see that נדרים, nedarim, at least
by foods, נדרים nedarim will be, will be בטל batel at a
certain point. It may be not necessarily the same case for things
which are not consumed. We're going to see it a little bit
later as well, the מחלוקת machloket רש"י Rashi and the ר"ן. Ran.
We'll get into that. Okay. מן הדבר ונתערב אם יש בו בנותן
טעם. Min hadavar v'nitarev im yesh bo b'noten ta'am. If it has
בנותן טעם, b'noten ta'am, if it's enough of it that it gives
a flavor, אסור. asur. הנודר מן היין. HaNoder min ha-yayin. What if
a person takes a נדר neder from wine? And this is different
from a נדר נזיר. neder nazir.
It's interesting to note that if you, at least if you have
the right לשון, lashon, you can avoid becoming a נזיר nazir but
still take a נדר neder not to drink wine or not to,
that wine should be forbidden to you, I should say.
However, in מסכת נזיר Masechet Nazir we'll see that even mentioning one
aspect of the איסורים issurim related to a נזיר nazir will make
you a נזיר nazir under different circumstances. So נזירות neziroot kind of
extends because נזירות neziroot is not just I made becoming טמא מת
tameh meis אסור assur and I made wine and grape products אסור
assur and I made cutting the hair אסור, assur, but that those
are all three together part of a status of a נזיר nazir
as a person. And נזיר nazir as a person therefore has certain
מצוות mitzvos and that's different than just saying that wine is אסור.
assur. So if you say I'm a נזיר nazir for drinking wine,
that would really make you a whole נזיר. nazir. But this, you
take a נדר neder from wine, it's just the wine and nothing
else. So if you take a נדר neder not to drink wine,
הנודר מן היין, hanoder min hayayin, with wine we don't go by
the טעם. ta'am. It's not like the meat. If you would, you
would be permitted to eat a cooked dish, Beef Bourguignon or something,
or Coq au Vin, that is some kind of a dish prepared
with wine that the wine really gives a strong flavor to the
dish. You know that it has wine in it, nonetheless it is
not drinking wine. It is eating a beef stew that happens to
have wine as a significant ingredient.
אמר קונם יין זה שאיני טועם, Amar konam yayin zeh she'eini to'eim,
but if a person said this wine I will not taste by
a נדר, neder, ונפל לתבשיל venafal letavshil and
קל וחומר kal vachomer if it was put in intentionally, אם יש
בו בנותן טעם הרי זה אסור, im yesh bo benosein ta'am harei
zeh assur, then if it gives a flavor it's אסור assur because
we said that the principle of נותן טעם nosein ta'am would only
apply just like we saw before that the later תנאים Tannaim in
the משנה Mishnah were explaining רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon position, that נותן
טעם nosein ta'am applies only in a case of בשר זה basar
zeh or יין זה, yayin zeh, this piece of meat gives a
טעם, ta'am, but not meat in general to give a טעם. ta'am.
Because if I say I'm not going to eat meat, then if
I'm eating a stew that tastes like meat, that's not enough for
it to be meat. But if I say this piece of meat
is אסור, assur, then even if it gives its flavor over, it's
going back to the original piece that I made אסור. assur. Yes.
So does this נותן טעם nosein ta'am carry over to כשרות Kashrus
regarding
סתם יינם? stam yeinam?
So
סתם יינם stam yeinam I'm not going to be able to answer
this right now, actually. The one thing that I can tell you
right now is that the principle of ביטול bitul for סתם יינם
stam yeinam is a much lower standard. It's not בטל בשישים, batel
beshishim, it's בטל בשישה batel beshisha for סתם יינם, stam yeinam, it's
one in six. But again ביטול bitul is accidentally and all different
things. But that may be related to some of this as well.
Again, the question of נותן טעם, nosein ta'am, well if it's one
in six for sure it's נותן טעם. nosein ta'am.
So we don't have to get into that now.
Interestingly enough, a bit apropos is the question of what's included in
the מנהג minhag that at least אשכנזים Ashkenazim have this year not
to eat meat during the nine days.
Because there are those who follow what the גמרא Gemara mentions about
שבוע שחל בו, shavua shechal bo, the week that תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av falls. And this year תשעה באב Tisha B'Av is on Sunday,
so there is no week that תשעה באב Tisha B'Av falls in,
at least according to the opinion that we פסקן pasken by. Well
it's on שבת, Shabbos, but this is a מחלוקת, machlokes, but the
way we פסקן... pasken... Okay but
the גמרא Gemara says that we reduce our שמחה, simcha, that doesn't
necessarily mean the halachic נפקא מינה nafka mina at least from the
גמרא, Gemara, but the אשכנזי Ashkenazi community has adopted for sure certain
מנהגים minhagim and other communities as well. So the מנהג minhag not
to eat meat during the nine days of תשעה באב Tisha B'Av
or during שבוע שחל בו. shavua shechal bo. So what about, can
you eat a dish which is technically פליישיג fleishig if it was
made with chicken broth or something, but you can't taste it, it
has no טעם ta'am of meat, or even it has no pieces
of meat?
I can tell a story. I went to a Chinese restaurant with
a friend during the nine days one year, and we were asking
about the food that they had there. Even the vegetarian dishes they
told us actually many of them were prepared with chicken broth, something
important for vegetarian people to know as well as for us to
know during the nine days. One of us was מחמיר machmir and
one of us wanted to be מקיל, makeil, but we ended up
going to a different restaurant. So I can't tell you who was
who. The other question... Yes.
סתם יינם stam yeinam is wine produced or handled by non-Jews which
is not, has not been used for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. There's
a דאורייתא d'oraisa prohibition on using things or consuming foods that were
used for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. There's a rabbinic concern against wine
produced or handled by non-Jews which is in some ways an extension
of the prohibition on יין נסך, yayin nesech, the wine used in
idolatrous libations. Alternatively, it may be related to more broader concerns about
intermingling and friendships and social relationships with non-Jews.
And it falls into the similar category of בישול עכו"ם, bishul akum,
food prepared by non-Jews, פת עכו"ם, pas akum, bread made by non-Jews,
and other things like that.
And some of the הלכות halachos are rather extensive and it's important,
you know, that's a big reason why we rely on kosher wines
rather than... the wines that are out in the marketplace and things
like that. Does the מנהג Minhag of not eating meat during the
nine days also apply to a piece of chicken? Is chicken the
same as meat? You know, here we saw this discussion if a
person says בשר Basar maybe it only applies to certain kinds of
בשר, Basar, we're not sure, but the מגן אברהם Magen Avraham in
שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says that we really are מחמיר Machmir against
basically all of these things. At least the מגן אברהם's Magen Avraham
opinion, there may be other opinions in the אחרונים Achronim as well
that we would be more lenient to allow, for example, like my
story, the opinion who wanted to say to eat the פליישיג Fleishig
vegetarian Chinese food that had no pieces of meat in it but
it was made with a chicken broth. Okay.
The big ר״ן. Ran. So the big ר״ן Ran is a discussion
about the principle of דבר שיש לו מתירין. Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin.
So דבר שיש לו מתירין, Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin, something which can
be made אסור Asur or will become, sorry, can be made מותר
Mutar or will become מותר. Mutar. So the ר״ן Ran asks a
question, so we have a principle in the laws of ביטול Bittul
that if something which is prohibited falls into a pot, you know,
your
piece of pork falls into your cholent, you know, or something like
that or a drop of milk falls into your cholent. And those
kinds of cases, those are all across יורה דעה Yoreh Deah in
learning כשרות. Kashrus. So one of the problems with ביטול Bittul or
one of the cases where ביטול Bittul shouldn't work is a case
of דבר שיש לו מתירין, Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin, something which...
so
something which can or will become permissible later is דבר שיש לו
מתירין. Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin. It will become permissible or it can
become permissible, and therefore it is not בטל. Batul. The רמב״ם Rambam
gives a few examples, including number one,
חדש. Chadash. חדש Chadash is grain before the עומר Omer sacrifice is
brought, or before in this in our case when there's no more
עומר Omer sacrifice, before the second day of פסח. Pesach. And so
חדש, Chadash, grain products, particularly in ארץ ישראל, Eretz Yisrael, perhaps as
well outside of ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael as well, חדש Chadash is
an איסור דאורייתא Issur DeOraisa to consume those grain products. And because
it's דבר שיש לו מתירין, Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin, it will become
permissible after the second day of פסח, Pesach, then at this point
permitted later and therefore we would say that it's not בטל. Batul.
So a piece of חדש Chadash bread fell into or חדש Chadash
מצה Matzah perhaps, חדש Chadash flour fell into a basket of ישן
Yashan
breads or flour, then it would not be בטל. Batul.
Not ever or until the end of?
It would not be בטל... Batul... ah, so it would be, once
it becomes מותר, Mutar, then it's fine. That's the whole point of
דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin according to רש״י. Rashi.
According to רש״י Rashi in ביצה Beitzah on דף ג, Daf Gimmel,
רש״י Rashi says the reason behind דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar Sheyesh
Lo Matirin not being בטל Batul is more or less you should
just wait. Why do you need to rely on ביטול? Bittul? Why
do you need to nullify it in the mixture? Just wait, it
will become permissible. The other example which gets commonly cited is a
question of חמץ Chametz on פסח. Pesach. חמץ Chametz is only forbidden
on פסח, Pesach, but after פסח Pesach it's מותר. Mutar. So if
a piece of חמץ Chametz falls into my מצה Matzah ball soup,
or maybe מצה Matzah ball soup is a bad example for those
who keep the געבראכטס, Gebrochts, but maybe a piece of חמץ Chametz
falls into my sponge cake or something like this or falls into
my chicken soup, then what do I do? Well, it's not בטל
Batul because it's חמץ Chametz that fell into kosher for פסח Pesach
and it's דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin because at
the end of פסח Pesach it will become permissible. However, the מרדכי
Mordechai disagrees with the רמב״ם. Rambam. The מרדכי Mordechai says חמץ Chametz
on פסח Pesach is not דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar Sheyesh Lo
Matirin because every year חמץ Chametz is forbidden again on פסח Pesach
again. So it never becomes totally מותר. Mutar. חמץ Chametz has a
vacillating kind of a status, on again off again, and so it
would not fall under the same category. So the ר״ן Ran here
has a big מחלוקת Machlokes with רש״י. Rashi. I just mentioned to
you the רש״י Rashi from ביצה. Beitzah. רש״י Rashi says the whole
point of דבר שיש לו מתירין Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin not being
בטל Batul is because it... because you might as well wait. The
ר״ן Ran here tries to lay out a much more conceptual explanation.
He disagrees with רש״י, Rashi, and he says look, aren't נדרים Nedarim
דבר שיש לו מתירין? Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin? Because you can always
just ask, you know, you can do שאלה Sheilah on your נדר,
Neder, you can ask someone to be מתיר Matir your נדר.
Neder. But that's not thing on its own, that's completely different.
Ah, okay, so that's a good question.
How about you said a נזיר? Nazir? If you say I'm going
to be a נזיר Nazir for thirty days, then afterwards, you know,
then the יין Yayin will be מותר Mutar on its own because
you don't have to do anything, you know.
Okay, so that's an interesting question. Do we consider נדרים, Nedarim, because
we said here from the משנה Mishna it sounds like נדרים, Nedarim,
if something that was made אסור Asur by a נדר Neder fell
into a mixture, that that should be, we could rely on ביטול,
Bittul, and that would sound like it's not דבר שיש לו מתירין,
Davar Sheyesh Lo Matirin, but the ר״ן Ran seems to think that
it is. And he goes through this whole thing, and the ר״ן's
Ran explanation connects the idea of דבר שיש לו מתירין, Davar Sheyesh
Lo Matirin, which ביטול Bittul does not apply because it will become
permissible later, then you can't nullify it now, compares it to the
question of מין במינו. Min BeMino. מין במינו Min BeMino is again
a case where ביטול Bittul would not apply. The example from the
גמרא Gemara in מנחות Menachos is there on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
we have a requirement to mix the blood of the פר, Par,
the Bull blood, with the blood of the שעיר, se'ir, the goat's
blood, and yet the תורה Torah even after they've been mixed, references,
calls them the blood of the פר par and the blood of
the שעיר se'ir separately, even though there's much more blood of the
ox than there is of the goat, we would think that it
would be בטל. batel. So it's proof that מין במינו, min bemino,
the same thing mixed together, ox blood and goat blood together are
both blood, so it's מין במינו, min bemino, one type in itself,
that nonetheless,
it would not be בטל batel because they are the same. And
so the way the ר"ן Ran explains that and he then will
extend that argument to דבר שיש לו מתירים davar she-yesh lo matirin
is that something which the whole point of how ביטול bitul works
is there are two different objects here, two different statuses, two different
halachic cases. But if they're the same, if they're both blood, then
they don't become בטל batel because there's no clash, there's no conflict.
So it will remain ox blood and goat blood because they're both
blood. They're too similar to contradict each other, so they don't need
to contradict, so they don't need to become בטל. batel. So the
ר"ן Ran says further, even an object's status as אסור asur and
מותר mutar is enough of a thing to make them different enough
that they conflict and one should be בטל batel in the other.
So the way we say
איסור, issur, something which is prohibited can become בטל batel in something
that's permitted is because they contradict. אסור asur and מותר mutar contradict,
but דבר שיש לו מתירים davar she-yesh lo matirin which will become
permissible or has the potential to become permissible, even a נדר neder
for example, at least according to the ר"ן's Ran initial suggestion but
but he's rejected, but because דבר שיש לו מתירים davar she-yesh lo
matirin is not a דבר האסור, davar ha-asur, it's not a piece
of something prohibited because it will become permissible later, then ביטול bitul
would not work. Okay.
Any questions? Yes. So that regarding the חמץ chametz after פסח Pesach
though, it's not actually דבר שיש לו מתירים, davar she-yesh lo matirin,
right? It's I mean, if I never sold your חמץ chametz at
all, if I didn't do anything to it, it would never become
מותר, mutar, right? After פסח? Pesach?
But that's only a דרבנן. derabbanan. You're talking about the איסור issur
of חמץ שעבר עליו הפסח, chametz she-avar alav ha-Pesach, חמץ chametz that
was owned by a Jew during פסח, Pesach, but that's only a
rabbinic prohibition as a קנס, knas, as a punishment for not getting
rid of your חמץ. chametz. That's not actually intrinsic to the prohibition
of חמץ. chametz.
Okay, but then don't they does that affect this? No. Why?
I mean like דרבנן... derabbanan...
Because the
the nature of the object is not fundamentally חמץ chametz after פסח
Pesach is מותר. mutar. This חמץ chametz which I happen to own
because the Rabbis told me I have a punishment for keeping it,
so that's something separate. That's not because it's חמץ. chametz.
It's okay to eat it from the דאורייתא? de'oraisa?
So it is a מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah de'oraisa not to own חמץ
chametz on פסח, Pesach, but if you broke that מצוה דאורייתא mitzvah
de'oraisa and kept חמץ chametz on פסח, Pesach, after פסח, Pesach, the
חמץ chametz would be permissible מדאורייתא, mide'oraisa, but מדרבנן miderabbanan the Rabbis
said even that חמץ, chametz, even after פסח Pesach remains prohibited because
of this קנס. knas. It's a punishment for having broken the דאורייתא.
de'oraisa. And this is something that people run into trouble with sometimes
with the grocery stores right after פסח. Pesach. Different שולן shuls send
out a list, don't go to this grocery store, don't go to
this grocery store, maybe it was owned by a Jewish person who
didn't sell the חמץ chametz or the company, certain companies are owned
by Jews and they don't sell their חמץ chametz and then their
products get filtered through, so you have to avoid maybe certain products
or certain grocery stores until a little bit after. Okay, so we
just finished this משנה. mishnah. This משנה mishnah had a few different
interesting examples, so now we see the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara
on the top of נ"ב עמוד א'... nun beis amud aleph... on
נ"ב, nun beis, גמרא Gemara says ורמינהו, urminhu, we're have a contradiction
against what we just saw in the משנה. mishnah. מן העדשים... min
ha-adashim... if a person took a נדר neder against עדשים, adashim, lentils,
אסור באשישים. asur ba-ashishim. He is prohibited to eat אשישים. ashishim. אשישים
ashishim sounds like some kind of either bread, according to the מפרש,
mefaresh, bread that was mixed with flour lentil flour and also regular
flour, or something like this in some it's a different method of
preparation is the point. I think another explanation, אשישים ashishim something the
lentils are prepared with honey or something like this, but so you
would think, okay, so change in the preparation in some sense. If
I took the lentils, ground them up and baked them into bread,
that's different than lentils. Nonetheless, אסור באשישים. asur ba-ashishim. I still remain
prohibited even though it's undergone this change. Shouldn't that contradict what we
said about the קום, kum, the whey of the milk, that even
though the milk has undergone a transformation, that nonetheless this the קום,
kum, the whey, would be permitted according to the תנא קמא. Tanna
Kamma. So it sounds like this source about the lentils contradicts the
תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. But רבי יוסי מתיר Rabbi Yose matir and
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose would permit אשישים. ashishim. And רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yose is the one who says that whey would be prohibited and
רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says here the אשישים ashishim are permitted. So
that seems like again, it doesn't fit with רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose
position and it doesn't fit with תנא קמא's Tanna Kamma position. איפכא?
Ipcha? Right.
לא
קשיא, La kashya,
מר כי אתריה ומר כי אתריה. mar ki atra u-mar ki atra.
We've seen this answer already before. No, no, no, don't try to
build me a whole conceptual explanation for why רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose
will hold like this and why תנא קמא Tanna Kamma holds like
this, no... The whole thing they're arguing about is nothing to do
with the status of whey is nothing to do with the status
of אשישים. ashishim. It's only מר כאתריה מר כאתריה. mar ke-atreih mar
ke-atreih. Each in their own place they use a different word to
describe these things. In רבי יוסי's Rabbi Yose place nobody calls אשישים
ashishim עדשים adashim still. Nobody calls it lentils anymore. You just say
if I want a bowl of lentils, you're going to get a
bowl of lentils. You're not going to get a lentil cake. And
therefore רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says it's not included in the נדר,
neder, but תנא קמא Tanna Kamma of this
ברייתא braita would.
Okay candy lentils, it's an interesting question. Right? So that's part of
the question. And the case of whey as well. If a person
asks for a glass of milk, you give them whey, they'll be
disappointed, or something like that. So it really depends again we said
by לשון בני אדם. lashon bnei adam. So מר כאתריה מר כאתריה,
mar ke-atreih mar ke-atreih, they each follow the vernacular or the word
choice in their place. People go by what you mean when you
say it. That's the whole point of נדרים nedarim is that your
words have a halachic meaning, so if your words have halachic meaning
then we actually have to go by not only what you say
but also what the word means to you. Okay מר
כאתריה מר כאתריה. mar ke-atreih mar ke-atreih. דרבנן קרי לחלבא חלבא ולקומא
קומא derabbanan kari le-chalba chalba u-le-kuma kuma because the Rabbis, the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma calls milk milk and whey
whey. באתרא דרבנן be-atra de-rabbanan in the place of the Rabbis they
call חלבא חלבא ולקומא קומא. chalba chalba u-le-kuma kuma. They call the
milk milk and the whey whey. באתרא דרבי יוסי be-atra de-Rabbi Yose
in the place of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose לקומא נמי קרי ליה
קומא דחלבא le-kuma nami kari lei kuma de-chalba because in the place
of רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose they called whey not just סתם stam
a whey, they call it milk whey. They call it milk whey,
it has the word milk in it, so that sounds like it
really should be included. Interesting point, my brother says that in the
part of Virginia where he lives, they don't call a pen a
pen, they call it an ink pen. So an ink pen is
to be very specific as opposed to perhaps a pencil or something
else.
What's a pen then?
What's a pen? If you say pen, people would be a little
bit confused. So what's just סתם stam whey? It's milk whey, you
know, you have to be specific, is that to be confused or...
It
lends
interesting context to the question of what's a Milky Way... but
so I have to keep making puns. Come on, they're good puns
here. What about candy company based on...
so there you go. And the other question is for example a
person says oh what if I take a נדר neder not to
eat chocolate or if I eat a נדר neder not to eat
candy and then something comes along. רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein
has a long תשובה teshuva about about Raisinets. What's the ברכה bracha
on Raisinets? Are Raisinets chocolate-covered raisins or are they raisin-filled chocolates? You
know this is a whole question when you eat you know you
eat all these horrible chocolate assortments and they have the red thing
and the rum balls and this and that, they're all terrible.
So you know so you're not buying... right I don't buy them
I just get them as... whatever you know...
what do you say...
so if I remember correctly רב משה פיינשטיין Rav Moshe Feinstein has
this whole long thing where he says you should say ברכה bracha
really on both or if you... better to have raisins there on
the side or another piece of fruit and say בורא פרי העץ
borei pri ha-etz on that.
But if you don't?
Other פוסקים poskim go through that and then another פוסק posek I
think רב שלמה זלמן אויערבאך Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach even... yeah I
think it's רב שלמה זלמן אויערבאך Rav Shlomo Zalman Auerbach says that
the ברכה bracha on chocolate to begin with should be בורא פרי
העץ. borei pri ha-etz. So the whole thing should be בורא פרי
העץ, borei pri ha-etz, chocolate and raisins. Okay let's keep going.
לקומא נמי קרי ליה קומא דחלבא. le-kuma nami kari lei kuma de-chalba.
תניא. tanya. הנודר מן החלב, ha-noder min he-chalav, if a person takes
a נדר neder not to drink milk or not to benefit from
the milk, מותר בקום. mutar be-kum. Ah he's permitted to eat the
the whey. That's like the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, right? מן הקום
מותר בחלב. min ha-kum mutar be-chalav. And if he took a נדר
neder not to get benefits from the whey then he's permitted to
get from the milk like we said as that was agreed to
לכולי עלמא le-kulei alma in our משנה. mishna. Okay. מן הקום
מותר בחלב. min ha-kum mutar be-chalav. מן החלב מותר בגבינה, min he-chalav
mutar be-gevina, if he takes a נדר neder not to get from
milk then he's מותר בגבינה mutar be-gevina he could eat cheese. מן
הגבינה מותר בחלב, min ha-gevina mutar be-chalav, if you take a נדר
neder not to eat cheese you're allowed to drink milk. מן הרוטב
מותר בקיפה, min ha-rotev mutar be-kippa, if you take a נדר neder
not to drink gravy then you're still allowed to eat the cracklings.
מן הקיפה מותר ברוטב min ha-kippa mutar be-rotev and if you took
a נדר neder not to eat cracklings then you're allowed to eat
the gravy. אם אמר בשר זה עלי, im amar basar zeh alay,
this meat is forbidden to me, אסור בו וברוטבו ובקיפה. assur bo
u-ve-rotvo u-ve-kippa. Then it's forbidden the meat and the gravy and the
cracklings. Just like we saw from רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon position as
explained by the later תנאים, tannaim, it makes sense that the flavor
of the meat would apply in a case where you said בשר
זה. basar zeh.
But not if you like poured on a separate gravy you made,
right?
Correct. But the... I mean if it was cooked together in some
way, again we have to wonder what their רוטב rotev was. It
sounds like their רוטב rotev is presumably the the sauce that the
meat was cooked in in some way or the stew that the
meat was cooked in in some way. You bake the chicken and
the drippings go into the pan. So that's that's part of that
רוטב. rotev. It's not a separate sauce that you keep in the
fridge. But maybe, that would be an interesting question. If I have
a designated you know I put barbecue sauce on my chicken every
time that I have chicken, so I think of that as chicken
sauce. Does that in some way become connected to the chicken? I
would think not. It sounds like here they're talking about טעם, taam,
but maybe there's room to suggest that that even becomes connected to
the chicken somehow. You associate with it.
Right exactly the association. It becomes connected to the idea of eating
chicken for me, so maybe that would still be included in the
נדר. neder. I'm not sure, I don't think that would be the
case, but it's...
It sounds like here they're talking about טעם, taam, but maybe there's
room to suggest that that even becomes connected to the chicken some
way. Like it's associated with... Right, exactly, the association. It becomes connected
to the idea of eating chicken for me, so maybe that would
still be included in the נדר. neder. I'm not sure, I don't
think that would be the case, but it's an interesting suggestion. Okay.
מיתיבי. Meitivi. איבעית אימא, Iveis eima, בשר זה עלי, Basar zeh alai,
אסור בו וברוטבו ובקיפה. asur bo u'v'rotvo u'v'kipah. והתניא מן היין Vehatanya
min hayayin if a person takes a נדר neder from wine, מותר
בתבשיל שיש בו טעם יין. mutar b'tavshil sheyesh bo taam yayin. You're
permitted to eat a cooked dish that has the flavor of wine.
אמר קונם יין זה שאיני טועם ונפל לתוכו תבשיל אם יש בו
טעם יין הרי זה אסור. Amar konam yayin zeh she'eini to'em venafal
le-tocho tavshil im yesh bo ta'am yayin harei zeh asur. And these
are all things that we already saw in the משנה Mishna quoted
in another ברייתא. Braitah. Okay.
There's a distinction here about
prohibiting wine and prohibiting not just this wine but also in regard
to my tasting.
Yeah, okay, so the difference between שאיני טועם she'eini to'em or that
יין זה אסור
עלי.
yayin zeh
asur alai. I don't think the נדר neder really cares that much
about it because the whole point of taking it as a נדר
neder is that you're making the wine forbidden. It's an interesting point
though about the לשון. lashon. Why is it יין זה איני טועם,
yayin zeh eini to'em, I'm not going to taste, and we said
בשר זה אסור עלי, basar zeh asur alai, it's prohibited. Why didn't
you say בשר זה שאיני טועם? basar zeh she'eini to'em? We saw
something similar in the משנה. Mishna. Our משנה Mishna said בשר זה
שאיני טועם, basar zeh she'eini to'em, right?
No, it said בשר זה עלי. basar zeh alai. I don't know
a good answer for that. I would think that the נדר neder
would be the same. שאיני טועם, she'eini to'em, I'm not going to
taste, and אסור עלי, asur alai,
maybe there's a difference between איסורי הנאה issurei hana'ah and איסורי אכילה,
issurei achilah, but I don't know where to go with that exactly.
Okay, let's go to the next משנה. Mishna. We keep going. הנודר
מן הענבים, Ha-noder min ha-anavim, if a person takes a נדר neder
from grapes, מותר ביין. mutar b'yayin. It's permitted to drink wine. This
sounds like something similar to what we said even about the whey
and קל וחומר kal v'chomer with grapes and wine is that the
process of producing wine from grapes is such a change, you don't
think of wine as grapes. It's not grapes anymore, it's wine. Or
grape juice either, right? Or even grape juice we have to get
into, but the point is that especially because הלכה halacha considers wine
a new status, a significant status, the wine itself is no longer
anything to do with grapes. It's not grapes anymore, it's wine. מן
הזיתים מותר בשמן Min ha-zeitim mutar b'shamen and if you take a
נדר neder from olives, you're permitted to get olive oil. Interesting, these
two examples and no other examples of fruit juices. הלכה halacha considers
olive oil and grape wine to be two of the seven משקים.
mashkim. There are seven משקים, mashkim, seven liquids that have a הלכתי
halachic significance for certain aspects in הלכה halacha including טומאה וטהרה tumah
v'taharah that certain liquids can transmit impurity or can become impure in
certain ways.
And so the only seven liquids that that would apply to are
wine and oil, blood, water, milk, dew, and דבש,
dvash, honey.
And so those seven and no other liquid. So if you had
orange juice, orange juice is not מכשיר. machshir. Orange juice is not
a משקה. mashkeh. So it doesn't, it wouldn't work for that. It's
not considered to be in some sense any different than an orange.
It didn't undergo a הלכתי halachic change. But wine and possibly oil
as well are designated special ברכות brachot for the fact that they've
undergone that change from being grapes and olives into being wine and
oil.
Isn't orange juice like most fruit juices mostly water?
Even well, all fruits are mostly water. Human beings are also mostly
water. Steak is mostly water. So it doesn't make sense to say
that just because it's mostly water that it's water. It's הלכתית halachically
different. I mean, for example, הלכה halacha notes the difference between dew
and water. Dew is a separate liquid from water. So yeah.
So how does this relate to a נזיר Nazir and also our
custom on the nine days that no products wine or grapes or
grape juice?
I would think that during the nine days there should be no
prohibition around eating grapes for us. It's not wine, it's grapes. You're
eating grapes, it's a fruit. You say העץ ha-etz on a grape.
And not to eat anything...
I personally have not had such a custom. I don't know, I
don't know about a custom not to eat grapes. For a נזיר,
Nazir, a נזיר Nazir is different. Grape juice? Grape juice is like
wine. We treat grape juice הלכתית halachically like wine for the most
part. It is important that...
because you need to be able
to make קידוש Kiddush on it. Well on שבת Shabbos for sure
you can make קידוש Kiddush no matter what. Oh, you're saying a
different point about what we said a few days ago. That... I'm
not going to get into that now. Question about the nine days:
grape juice should have the same status as wine as far as
I would think. The question that gets brought up all the time
is can you make הבדלה Havdalah on grape juice or on wine
because it's really after שבת Shabbos is over and it's become now
the you know the...
But I was saying נזיר Nazir is not as...
A נזיר Nazir is mentioned explicitly in the תורה. Torah.
No raisins, grapes, right?
Raisins, grapes, each of those distinct מצוות, mitzvot, right? Here there's a
distinction between grape and wine. And so a person takes a נדר
neder against just wine, then grapes are still permitted. Or if a
person takes a נדר neder against grapes, then wine is still permitted
because there's a transformation that undergoes between the grapes and the wine.
אמר קונם זיתים וענבים אלו שאיני טועם אסור בהם ובליוצא בהם. Amar
konam zeitim va-anavim eilu she'eini to'em asur ba-hem u-va-yotzei ba-hem. If you
said these grapes, these olives, and then you pressed them and made
wine or olive oil out of those fruits, אלו eilu these, just
like we said בשר זה, basar zeh, יין זה, yayin zeh, so
this is כל היוצא מהם kol ha-yotzei mei-hem
is also forbidden. Whatever comes from them. and out of them. So
we see just like meat can give a טעם, ta'am, give a
flavor from the meat itself that goes into the whole dish, and
wine can give a flavor that goes from the wine into the
whole dish, so too if you take grapes or olives and press
them to make wine and oil, so too if you really said
זה zeh or אלו, eilu, these ones explicitly, specifically, then whatever comes
out of them, even the טעם, ta'am, even the wine and oil,
will carry on the נדר neder status. But if you did not
say זה, zeh, then it would not. Okay. So בעי רמי בר
חמא. ba'ei Rami bar Chama. So Rebbi asked— Rami bar Chama asked—
אלו דוקא או שאיני טועם דוקא? eilu davka o she'eini to'em davka?
Is it really אלו, eilu, these ones דוקא davka specifically, or are
you saying שאיני טועם, she'eini to'em, I'm not going to taste, specifically?
אי סלקא דעתך, ei salka da'atach, if you would think, אלו דוקא,
eilu davka, that אלו, eilu, these ones specifically, שאיני טועם, she'eini to'em,
that I'm not going to taste— so sorry, אלו דוקא, eilu davka,
if I think it means אלו דוקא, eilu davka, meaning these ones
specifically, then שאיני טועם למה לי? she'eini to'em lama li? Why do
I have to say שאיני טועם, she'eini to'em, I'm not going to
taste? Why not just say
זיתים אלו אסורים עלי? zeitim eilu assurim alai? So this was exactly
your question before,
which was a point of why do we have to say שאיני
טועם? she'eini to'em? Why do we have to say I'm not going
to taste? Why not just say אסורים עלי? assurim alai? So we
say שאיני טועם למה לי הא קמשמע לן דאף על גב דאמר
שאיני טועם אי דאמר אלו מיסר ואי לא לא. she'eini to'em lama
li ha kamashma lan de'af al gav de'amar she'eini to'em ei de'amar
eilu missar ve'ei lo lo. Because it comes to say that even
though אף על גב דאמר שאיני טועם, af al gav de'amar she'eini
to'em, that I said I will not taste, אי דאמר אלו, ei
de'amar eilu, if I said these ones, מיסר, missar, it becomes forbidden.
Meaning why? I said these grapes I will not taste. So I
would think, oh, I will not taste grapes, but I will taste
wine, I would be permitted to drink wine. No, because you said
אלו, eilu, that comes to override.
But "these" doesn't actually refer to those particular grapes, and I could
have a bottle of wine someone else made with different grapes?
You would be able to have another bottle of wine made from
different grapes because you said— it says, I will not eat these
grapes. I made these...
Like these type of grapes? In other words...
I don't think type of grapes. These grapes. In this batch... It's
not this batch, I don't think so. I think it's these grapes.
You're saying literally in front of you.
It's right what's in front of you. You say זה, zeh, you're
pointing at it, you know.
And so if you say—
It makes no sense whatsoever.
Why does that make no sense?
Those grapes that are sitting right in front of you? Yeah. It's
two years later that you...
Okay, so what?
But what I did is I made these grapes and everything that
comes out of them will be prohibited. And then I took these
grapes and I pressed them and made a bottle of wine.
Yeah, but what if someone— but it doesn't say that here.
The משנה mishnah said אסור בהן, assur bahem, they are prohibited, וביוצא
מהן, uvayotze mehen, and whatever comes out, because you said אלו, eilu,
because you said these ones. So רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama
says, if you would think that it's אלו דוקא, eilu davka, these
grapes specifically, then why do I care whether you'll say שאיני טועם,
she'eini to'em, I'm not going to taste?
Of course it makes a difference! I could sell them!
This is between— No, but why— meaning why do I have to
include the words שאיני טועם she'eini to'em in the משנה? mishnah? No,
because what do you mean?
If I say these grapes are אסורים עלי בהנאה, assurim alai b'hana'ah,
then I can't sell them either. If I say שאיני טועם, she'eini
to'em, I just can't eat them but I can still sell them.
But I think in the context at least here, we're talking all
of these are about— they should be— I mean, again with a
נדר, neder, it's always going to be אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah.
No, if I say these grapes are אסור assur for me to
eat, טועם, to'em, I can't eat them, I can sell them to
you.
Is that true? Did we say that? I don't remember.
Why wouldn't it be?
Because I think once you make the נדר, neder, it creates the
איסור. issur. You can't just make a נדר neder that makes it
only אסור באכילה assur b'achilah but not אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah.
What do you mean? If I say I can't eat this meat,
I can still sell it, right?
Why wouldn't I— but like what? Is it like קונם? konam? If
it's like קונם, konam, you can't get any הנאה hana'ah from it
at all. I thought—
we say a נדר neder is like דבר הנידר, davar hanidur, right?
It's like making it like a קרבן. korban. It's like making it,
you know... I have to go back. That's like second פרק perek
kind of a topic, right? I don't remember.
Actually, this we addressed— the point a little bit later on in
the גמרא. Gemara.
Oh, so then we'll keep going. All right.
So meaning if you did not say שאיני טועם, she'eini to'em, that
it would not. Okay. אמר רבא תא שמע. Amar Rava ta shema.
So Rava says, תא שמע, ta shema, קונם פירות האלו עלי קונם
הם לפי אסור בחילופיהם ובגידוליהם. konam peirot ha'eilu alai konam hem lefi
assur b'chilufieihem u'v'gidulieihem. So proof, something similar. Let's compare this to what
we just said about the grapes and the olives to the wine
and the oil. Let's compare it to the case that we already
saw. A person says קונם פירות אלו עלי, konam peirot eilu alai,
these fruits are אסור assur to me, or קונם הם לפי, konam
hem lefi, they are forbidden to my
mouth. אסור בחילופיהם ובגידוליהם. assur b'chilufieihem u'v'gidulieihem. It's prohibited, the money that
you get if you try to sell them— the money itself will
also be prohibited— and בגידוליהם, v'gidulieihem, if you plant the fruits and
then a new tree grows and it grows its own new grapes,
that's also prohibited. אהא ביוצא מהן מותר. aha b'yotze mehen mutar. But
you would think it only mentioned explicitly חילופיהם, chilufieihem, the money that
you exchange them for, or גידוליהם, gidulieihem, if you planted the fruits
and they grew into a new tree, but not יוצא מהן, yotze
mehen, if you pressed the grapes and made wine out of them,
that— that's יוצאי מהן, yotzei mehen, that's something different. אה הוא הדין
דאפילו ביוצאי מהן אסור. Ah hu hadin deafilu beyotzei mehen assur. No,
we should read it the opposite way. Nah, if we say גידוליהן
gidulieihen and חילופיהן, chilufieihen, we should also say יוצאי מהן yotzei mehen
is אסור. assur. אה והא עדיפא ליה לאשמועינן דחילופיהן כגידוליהן. Ah veha
adifa lei lashmuinan dechilufieihen kegidulieihen. No, the whole point of that משנה
Mishnah was just to teach us that חילופיהן chilufieihen are אסור assur
just like גידוליהן. gidulieihen. Why should I—כגידוליהן דמי—why kegidulieihen dami I should
only learn like that and I shouldn't have to have no connection
to what I think about יוצאי מהן. yotzei mehen. תא שמע שאיני
אוכל ושאיני טועם מותר בחילופיהן ובגידוליהן. Ta shema sheini ochel usheini toem
mutar bechilufieihen uvegidulieihen. אה, Ah, so what about in a case—so now
we'll read the next clause of the same thing—you didn't say פירות
אלו עלי peirot elu alai or קונם לפי, konam lephi, you said
שאיני אוכל sheini ochel or שאיני טועם. sheini toem. מאי? Mai? This
is exactly your question that if you said
only—sorry I didn't mention it before—if you say that I won't eat
it, it's only creating the איסור אכילה. issur achilah. Therefore חילופיהן chilufieihen
and גידוליהן, gidulieihen, if you sell them and get the money or
you plant them and grow a new tree, well you didn't eat
it, so you didn't violate your נדר. neder. Your נדר neder was
only not to eat it, but not to not get any הנאה.
hana'ah.
So this answers רמי בר חמא's Rami Bar Chama question.
So it seems to be exactly, that's the point. So this is
being brought by רבא Rava to seem to be as an answer
to רמי בר חמא. Rami Bar Chama. So we'll see, מותר בחילופיהן
ובגידוליהן, mutar bechilufieihen uvegidulieihen, then the money or the gross of it
will be permitted. הא היוצא מהן אסור? Ha hayotzei mehen assur? Couldn't
you still say that יוצא מהן, yotzei mehen, meaning the wine or
the oil that comes out, would be still prohibited? And therefore that
that would fit the משנה, Mishnah, but that would not help explain
רמי בר חמא. Rami Bar Chama. דאי לא נסיב ברישא יוצא מהן
לא נסיב נמי בסיפא יוצא מהן. De'i lo nasiv bereisha yotzei mehen
lo nasiv nami beseifa yotzei mehen. So just like we can't connect
it to יוצא מהן yotzei mehen in the רישא, reisha, the first
part, where you said פירות אלו עלי, peirot elu alai, and we
said יוצא מהן yotzei mehen we can't connect to that at all.
אה, Ah, it
shouldn't—יוצא מהן yotzei mehen should be less strict or more strict on
either case—we just can't compare. יוצא מהן yotzei mehen does not fall
into the same categorization as חילופיהן chilufieihen and גידוליהן. gidulieihen. Frankly, it
seems to be a pretty good
point. Wait, what are we saying? Meaning, we said like this. We
had two parts. We had the רישא reisha and in the רישא
reisha we said פירות אלו
עלי.
peirot elu
alai. And in the סיפא seifa we said שאיני
טועם. sheini toem. So שאיני טועם sheini toem we said it's מותר
mutar to have
חילופיהן וגידוליהן. chilufieihen uvegidulieihen. Here we said it's אסור assur to have
חילופיהן וגידוליהן. chilufieihen uvegidulieihen. So the question is, how would we then
rule on the category of יוצא מהן? yotzei mehen? So we said
first, well maybe we should say—so also make here now a column,
יוצא מהן. yotzei mehen. So יוצא מהן yotzei mehen we thought, well
maybe יוצא מהן yotzei mehen should also be אסור. assur. We said,
no, we can't extend what the this says to apply to יוצא
מהן yotzei mehen as well. Maybe יוצא מהן yotzei mehen should still
be מותר. mutar. So we say, we don't know. And then we
read the סיפא. seifa. We said, אה, Ah, maybe we said מותר
חילופיהן וגידוליהן, mutar chilufieihen uvegidulieihen, then יוצא מהן yotzei mehen should be
אסור assur because it should be stricter than this. We also said
we can't compare that to that. So we don't know. Meaning we
have no good reason to say that יוצא מהן yotzei mehen should
be אסור assur compared to this case. Does that make sense? So
because there was two parts of the same—the same ברייתא, braita, okay,
or משנה. Mishnah. תא שמע אמר רבי יהודה מעשה ואסר רבי טרפון
עלי ביצים שנתבשלו בו. Ta shema amar Rabbi Yehuda ma'aseh ve'assar Rabbi
Tarfon alai beitzim shenitbashlu bo. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said the
case that was quoted in the משנה Mishnah that I was with
רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and
someone had taken a נדר neder from the meat—perhaps
it was רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda himself—he took a נדר neder from
eating meat, and רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon said you can't have the
eggs that are prepared with the meat. אמרו לו אימתי? Amru lo
ematai? So they responded to רבי טרפון, Rabbi Tarfon, in what case
did what you say apply? בזמן שאמר בשר זה עלי. Bizman she'amar
basar zeh alai. If you say בשר זה—this basar zeh meat—is forbidden.
שהנודר מן הדבר ונתערב באחר ויש בו בנותן טעם הרי זה אסור.
Shehanoder min hadavar venitariv be'acher veyesh bo benotein ta'am harei zeh assur.
If you made a נדר neder against one thing and it became
mixed with something else and it gives a flavor—it has enough of
it that it gives a flavor—הרי זה אסור. harei zeh assur. ובאלו
לא קמיבעיא לן דדווקא הוא. Uve'elu lo kamibaia lan dedavka hu. So
דווקא davka or לאו דווקא? lav davka? So this is going back
to רמי בר חמא's Rami Bar Chama question, so we're going to
try to say okay so we said that was a case where
you said בשר זה. basar zeh. However, הרי דאסור באלו? harei de'assur
be'elu? So what about אלו, elu, right? We said זה. zeh. בשר
זה. basar zeh. That was what you meant. But what about אלו—these
elu grapes? So it doesn't necessarily fit with רבי טרפון's Rabbi Tarfon
story because קמיבעיא לן דדווקא הוא. kamibaia lan dedavka hu. So should
we say that this should be—we should ask, right—is this like דווקא?
davka? And we're saying specifically זה, zeh, this one, and therefore it
doesn't—he didn't have to say שאיני טועם. sheini toem. We don't know
what the person who took the נדר neder said, we just said
הנודר מן הבשר. hanoder min habasar. He didn't say שאיני טועם. sheini
toem. So that sounds like רמי בר חמא's Rami Bar Chama first
case because he said it was just about the זה zeh or
the אלו דווקא, elu davka, but not about שאיני טועם sheini toem
that I won't taste it, right? ובשאיני טועם דווקא או לאו דווקא?
Uvesheini toem davka o lav davka? So we're still saying, so this
is going to raise the question now whether. whether it's דווקא davka
או לאו דווקא, o lav davka, whether we specifically focused on the
word זה zeh or אלו eilu or the phrase שאיני טועם. she'eini
toeim. They said, תא שמע tashma דג דגים. dag dagim. So now
we're going back to the משנה mishna we had yesterday. A person
takes a נדר neder against fish or fishes, דג dag or דגים,
שאיני טועם, dagim she'eini toeim. that I won't taste them, אסור בהן
בין גדולים בין קטנים בין חיים בין מבושלים, asur bahen bein gedolim
bein ketanim bein chayim bein mevushalim, whether they are large or small,
whether they are raw or cooked, ומותר צירי התרופה, u'mutar tzirei hatrufa,
the whatever it is, chopped up fish brine salad, tuna salad, something
like this, we don't know exactly what that is, ובציר u'vatzir and
the ציר, tzir, ציר tzir is some kind of a brine, but
again, ציר tzir is the juice that comes out of the fish.
But אמר רבא, amar Rava, וכבר יצא מהן. u'kvar yatza mehen. So
this seems to be trying to make an argument about יוצא מהן.
yotzei mehen. If I had grapes, right? Here are my grapes. And
then the grapes turn into wine at some point, right? That's a
transformation that has changed from the status it was at the time
the נדר neder was made into a new status. Grapes turn into
wine. That's what we say, יוצא מהן. yotzei mehen. With the fish,
here's a piece of fish, and then it got, the juice came
out of the fish. Okay? So this is the ציר. tzir. Okay?
So we would say the juice that comes out of the fish
should have the same status as the fish, and it says מותר,
mutar, right? The juice that squeezed out of the fish at some
point afterwards would be מותר, mutar, it would be permissible, and therefore
we should learn from that משנה mishna יוצא מהן, yotzei mehen, whatever
liquid is produced by these things is not included in the נדר.
neder. Yes. But when the wine made conscious every of you in
the bad you're smaut behind the mind it's not a fish it's
just behind you know whatever it happens. It's a very good question.
What your question is saying is doesn't the conscious creative process of
making wine make it much more of an independent entity separate from
the grapes different than just the ציר tzir from the fish? It's
a good question. But it seems to be the way the גמרא
Gemara is reading this, not like that. It seems to draw a
full analogy with them. And רבא Rava says, no, we're not talking
about this case. We're saying כבר יצא מהן. kvar yatza mehen. The
ציר tzir that is מותר, mutar, the ציר tzir that is permissible
to you even if you took a נדר neder against the fish,
is only the ציר tzir that had already come out of the
fish by the time you took the נדר, neder, not the ציר
tzir that was produced after. יוצא מהן, yotzei mehen, whatever comes out
of the דבר האסור davar ha'asur is still prohibited. However, if there
was juice already here in the time of the נדר, neder, then
that would be permissible because that wasn't included in the piece of
fish when you made the נדר. neder. So that רבא Rava explained,
and that way we can have a consistent ruling that יוצא מהן
yotzei mehen is separate from, sorry, the opposite, that it seems to
be a proof that יוצא מהן yotzei mehen would be permitted if
you said זה zeh or אלו, eilu, these specifically, because it's not
about שאיני טועם, she'eini toeim, because we even had the דגים dagim,
שאיני טועם. she'eini toeim, Fish I will not taste, but you did
not say דג זה. dag zeh. So it's the word זה, zeh,
זה דווקא zeh davka is what gives rise to the prohibition on
יוצא מהן. yotzei mehen. Let's try to get a bit of a
start on the next עמוד amud at least. We'll see how far
we get. Some people mentioned a concern about learning on תשעה באב.
Tisha B'av. Yes, רבא כבר יצא מהן. Rava kvar yatza mehen. That
רבא's Rava point is that the case of the fish, sorry, I'll
explain again, the case of the fish that the ציר tzir would
be permitted is which brine, which ציר? tzir? It's not ציר tzir
that comes out afterward. It's ציר tzir that had come out, that
was out even from beforehand, and therefore the ציר tzir that came
out afterward, after the time of the נדר, neder, would be included
in the fish, and therefore שאיני, she'eini, I said it wrong, sorry,
so good you pointed out, I have to go back over it,
sorry. רבא Rava is saying כבר יצא מהן. kvar yatza mehen. Whatever
came out beforehand is permitted because it's not part of the fish.
Whatever juice comes out of the fish after the נדר neder was
made was included because you said the word שאיני טועם. she'eini toeim.
I will not taste it. Therefore, it's proof we do not care
about the word זה, zeh, I'm very sorry I messed that up.
We don't care about the word זה. zeh. We care about שאיני
טועם. she'eini toeim. And שאיני טועם she'eini toeim means I won't taste
it, and that's what creates the איסור issur on יוצא מהן. yotzei
mehen. And that's the answer to רמי בר חמא's Rami bar Chama
question, because רמי בר חמא Rami bar Chama asked is it about
the word זה zeh or is it about the word שאיני טועם.
she'eini toeim. רבא's Rava answer, we would think that this would be
a proof one way, and רבא Rava says no, כבר יצא מהן,
kvar yatza mehen, כבר יצא מהן kvar yatza mehen means the ציר
tzir that's permitted is the ציר tzir that was already came out.
Whatever ציר tzir comes out afterward is יוצא מהן, yotzei mehen, is
the juice that comes out of a fish that was a דבר
האסור, davar ha'asur, and therefore the juice is prohibited. Ah, proof that
the שאיני טועם, she'eini toeim, I will not taste, is what creates
the איסור issur on יוצא מהן yotzei mehen and not the word
זה. zeh. Does that sound right? Does that work? Yeah. Maybe we
talk about it a little bit afterward if you want a bit
more clarification. And I'm sorry that I messed it up on the
first time around. The second time around sounds like it works better.
Okay. נג עמוד א, Nun gimmel amud aleph, right at the top.
The משנה mishna says, הנודר מן התמרים. hanoder min hatemarim. If a
person takes a נדר neder against dates, מותר בדבש. תמרים. mutar bidvash
temarim, So, if a person the person would be permitted with date
honey. The large matter of debate when the תורה Torah is talking
about דבש, dvash, are we talking about דבש תמרים dvash temarim or
דבש דבורים, dvash devorim, is it bee honey or date honey with
very important נפקא מינות nafka minas for many הלכות halachos including the
prohibition on putting honey into קרבנות, korbanot, there's a מצוה mitzvah לא
תעשה lo taaseh not to put yeast and honey into קרבנות, korbanot,
so does that apply to bee honey or date honey. When we
say ארץ זבת חלב ודבש, Eretz zavat chalav u'dvash, ארץ ישראל Eretz
Yisrael is a land that flows with milk and honey, does that
mean דבש תמרים dvash temarim and דבש דבורים? dvash devorim? Are there
a lot of bees or are there a lot of date trees?
A lot of the date trees have sadly been cut down and
burned down throughout much of ארץ ישראל's Eretz Yisrael history and some
of them have been replanted but not necessarily date palms but other
kinds of palm trees, so there are fewer dates nowadays. But that's
something else. Okay, so there's a lot because again we said before
about the seven משקין, mashkin, so the הלכה halacha about the seven
משקין mashkin is that the דבש dvash of the seven משקין mashkin
that counts as a liquid is דבש דבורים, dvash devorim, bee honey,
and not date honey. Why? We'll have to learn מסכת מכשירין. Masechet
Machshirin. But it comes up, there they from מדרש הלכה Midrash Halacha
and other places, I think one of the proofs even is from
the story of שמשון Shimshon when שמשון Shimshon kills the lion and
he takes the honey out of the lion carcass or whatever it
was, so that's something to do with that. So there are a
few other proofs for that but I think that it comes up
there, the question of again you have all these questions of you
have a honeycomb and the honey is dripping on the outside, so
it's a food that's covered with a liquid but the liquid came
out on its own, it didn't you didn't put it there, so
it's talking about bee honey, it's not talking about the date honey.
And again because only two fruits that are הלכתית halachically significant liquids
come out of them are grapes and olives, but not dates, because
the dates that you press to make honey, that date honey is
really just counts as syrup or the juice of the dates, it's
not a separate separate thing. Okay. So nevertheless, he still says he
still even though it's not count as a separate thing, you still
can have a date honey. No, you can, מותר בדבש mutar bidvash.
תמרים, temarim. you can, you can have it. Right, but you're saying
it would count as a syrup not a separate thing, but nevertheless
from נדרים nedarim it is a separate thing. It is a separate
thing enough, meaning it's not a separate משקה, mashkeh, it's not a
separate liquid, but it's a separate food. If I say תמרים, temarim,
I only mean the fruit, I don't mean the juice liquid produced
from it. Are you sure that honey doesn't come out of dates?
דבש תמרים dvash temarim in the משנה? Mishna? No, meaning it does,
the word דבש dvash is used for both date honey and bee
honey. The problem is for certain הלכות halachos there are certain prohibitions
or certain מצוות mitzvot that apply to honey, and then we have
to ask which honey is it talking about? I understand, did you
just state honey the only liquid that comes from fruit? No, meaning
the fruit the liquid that comes from fruits that has הלכתית halachic
significance in its own right are wine and oil, olive oil. For
שבת Shabbat also. Right. Okay, so we'll keep going. מסתונית Mistavnit from
the according to the מפרשים mefarshim היינו ענבים קשים מניחים בכרם כל
ימי הסתיו, haynu anavim kashim manichim bekerem kol yemei hastav, they're the
grapes that you leave in the vineyard all all fall all autumn
ועושים מהם חומץ ve'osim mehem chometz and you make vinegar from them.
Not exactly vinegar, it's something a bit different, basically thanks to having
a brother in the wine business I know a little bit about
some of these things. So the unripe grapes or grapes that would
never really become ripe and don't produce enough sugar, at least that's
what I think they're talking about, so you can press that and
that is like a grape juice that has a very strong high
level of malic acid and citric acid in the juice and it's
very sour in something similar to vinegar in a way. Alternatively they
could just be talking about grapes that were left on the vine
very very very long so they become very sugary and then you
make wine out of them and then you make vinegar out of
that wine and that will be the reason you make vinegar so
that it should be more sour presumably. Okay, so מותר בחומץ סתוונית.
mutar bechometz stavnit. So if you took a נדר neder not to
get benefit or not to eat these fall fall grapes, you would
still be permitted with the vinegar or whatever it is that's made
out of them. רבי יהודה בן בתירה אומר כל ששם תולדתו קרוי
עליו, Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer kol sheshem toldato karui alav, anything
that the name of what it is made out of is called
on it, meaning its name is called after what it's made out
of, like we saw with רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi about the קומא
דחלבא, kuma d'chalba, the whey of milk. So if the name is
included in its name, its the חומץ סתווניות, chometz stavniyot, it is
the vinegar made out of the fall grapes. So רבי יהודה בן
בתירה אומר כל ששם תולדתו קרוי עליו Rabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer
kol sheshem toldato karui alav הנודר ממנו אסור ביוצא ממנו וחכמים מתירין.
hanoder mimenu asur beyotze mimenu ve'chachamim matirin. So he's in disagreement with
the last משנה Mishna then? Because he'd disagree right, because we had
olive oil which we said was permitted. Olive oil but we only
call it שמן, shemen, we don't say שמן זיתים. shemen zeitim. Well
now we do. Well now we do, so maybe now the הלכה
halacha changed. Okay so we're going to see here in one second,
so we're going to see in a second, so grape juice, also
for grape juice, that'd be אסור assur according to it's an interesting
question. The next משנה Mishna is going to deal with the question
of when you say שמן shemen are we talking about שמן זיתים,
shemen zeitim, שמן שומשמין, shemen shumshumin, what about sesame oil, and so
the question would come what does what does the word really mean?
Do I say when I say do I have to say שמן
זיתים shemen zeitim to really mean שמן זיתים? shemen zeitim? Interesting point
in Arabic the word. So even petroleum oil is called after olive
oil. So if you're in an Arabic country, you know it that
way. Fill up your car. Exactly, so we're going to say that
any, you know, we have to understand on the one hand, we
really do want to say לשון בני אדם *lashon bnei adam*, נדרים
*nedarim* follow the way people speak and what they mean, but we
also go by the words that you use when you articulate the
נדר *neder* as well. And if those things, you know, עד שיהיו
דבריו ולבו שוים *ad she-yehiyu devarav ve-libo shavim*, ופירושם המעכב *u-ferusham ha-me-akev*...
right, and we have the sense of the until you're, you know,
when you're trying to be מתיר *matir* a נדר *neder* that your
לשון *lashon* and your לב *lev*, that your intent and the words
you use should be שוים *shavim*, they should be equivalent. So let's
see the גמרא *Gemara* here. חכמים *Chachamim*, היינו תנא קמא *hainu tanna
kamma*. So it sounds like the חכמים *Chachamim* here are the תנא
קמא *tanna kamma* from over there because we just saw about the
מחלוקת *machloket* between תנא קמא *tanna kamma* and רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi*,
that רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yossi* said that the whey that comes from
the milk is because of the קומא דחלבא *kuma de-chalba* and that's
why. So we just saw that it's called קומא דחלבא *kuma de-chalba*
and the reason the קומא דחלבא *kuma de-chalba* and that's why it's
considered part of the נדר *neder* against milk. So too the חכמים
*Chachamim* who allowed it, the whey from the milk. So it sounds
like our חכמים *Chachamim* here are the תנא קמא *tanna kamma* of
the משנה *mishnah* in this משנה *mishnah* because first it's הנודר מן
הדבש מותר בדבש תמרים *ha-noder min ha-dvash mutar bi-dvash temarim*. Right because
it's the same, it's the same חכמים *Chachamim*. It's the whey and
the חכמים *Chachamim* say no, so it's the same, it means throughout
the same תנא קמא *tanna kamma* and the same חכמים *Chachamim* before,
but it's the same מחלוקת *machloket*. So איכא בינייהו *ika beinaihu*, so
what's, so what's going to be the קונץ *kuntz* of the מחלוקת
*machloket* between them? איכא בינייהו חד דתניא כלל זה אמרו בשם רבי
אלעזר כל שדרכו לאכול ודרך היוצא ממנו לאכול *ika beinaihu chad de-tanya
klal zeh amru beshem Rabbi Elazar kol she-darko le-ekhol ve-derekh ha-yotzeh mimenu
le-ekhol*, meaning רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* now made
his own principle. Anything כל שדרכו לאכול *kol she-darko le-ekhol*, anything which
is edible on its own, and ודרך היוצא ממנו לאכול *ve-derekh ha-yotzeh
mimenu le-ekhol*, and you can eat the juice that comes out of
it, like grapes or like grapes or something like that, כגון תמרים
ודבש תמרים *kegon temarim u-dvash temarim*, נדר בו אסור ביוצא ממנו *nadar
bo assur be-yotzeh mimenu*. So if it's, so like dates and the
honey of dates, נדר בו *nadar bo* if you took a נדר
*neder* on it, meaning a נדר *neder* on the dates, then אסור
ביוצא ממנו *assur be-yotzeh mimenu*, then you're prohibited to get whatever comes
out of it. נודר מיוצא ממנו *noder mi-yotzeh mimenu*, and if you
took a נדר *neder* against what comes out of it, אסור בו
*assur bo*. I would've thought that. Then because he's saying if I
have a date and I squeeze it and the honey comes out,
the honey is really just something that was in the date, and
if I make a נדר *neder* against the honey, well the honey
is included inside the date to begin with, meaning this date, there's
no transformation going on, it's just a separation. I don't know. So
the honey is part of the date, so if I make a
נדר *neder* against dates then the honey is also prohibited and if
I make a נדר *neder* against the honey then the dates are
prohibited as well. Grape juice we said is different. Grape juice we
said is different. Grape juice and olive oil are different because they
have a different name and they have a different halakhic status. But
this is, but this is, it doesn't seem to be. But רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* is talking about, he said
כגון *kegon* like תמרים ודבש *temarim u-dvash*, meaning not like grapes and
wine. Meaning he was very specific then. Meaning he made a general
principle about everything in the world except for grapes and olives. He
talked about fish, he's talking about cheese, he's talking about milk and
foul grapes and dates and all other kinds of examples. And you
always not include that too? It's an interesting question, perhaps he disagrees
with the other position about wine and oil, it's a possibility, I
don't know. We'll have to see, we would have to interpret רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* to see how he goes.
Okay, here's ממנו נודר ממנו אסור בו *mimenu noder mimenu assur bo*.
כל שאין דרכו לאכול ודרך היוצא ממנו לאכול *kol she-ein darko le-ekhol
ve-derekh ha-yotzeh mimenu le-ekhol*. What about things which are themselves inedible but
then the liquids that can come out of them are edible? נודר
בו אין אסור אלא ביוצא ממנו *nadar bo ein assur ela be-yotzeh
mimenu*. Then if you make a נדר *neder* against them, then the
only thing that's prohibited is what comes out of them because not
even edible on its own. So obviously you were talking about whatever
comes out of it. The question people raise is what about the
oranges that people make orange juice out of are almost too sweet
to eat on their own, we so, it's not pleasure, again, it
depends on the orange. But okay. Okay, so אין דרכו לאכול והיוצא
ממנו לאכול נודר בו אין אסור אלא ביוצא ממנו *ein darko le-ekhol
ve-ha-yotzeh mimenu le-ekhol nadar bo ein assur ela be-yotzeh mimenu*, שלא נתכוין
זה אלא ליוצא ממנו *she-lo nitkaven zeh ela le-yotzeh mimenu*. The only
thing that you had intent for was the edible product that would
be produced from it. Can't think off the top of my head
of a good example of that. What are things which are themselves
inedible but have a product produced from them which is edible? Well,
you have to prepare them sometimes. You have to prepare them sometimes.
Coffee is an interesting example. Coffee beans are edible, but no one
eats them, but you could, meaning top, chocolate-covered coffee beans, right, things
like that. No one eats coffee, you just, you don't just eat
it, can't just eat the ground. Right. Try to think of another
good example, I can't think. Chestnuts. Chestnuts people eat. You eat them
raw. Yeah, but it's not about being raw, but it's about pressing
or squeezing them in some way. Some kind of juice that the
fruit itself isn't... I don't know. Okay, we'll keep going. Wait, so
what do we say about grapes? Well okay, this one hour. What
do we say about grape juice then? I don't know what רבי
שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* would say. Perhaps רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* does not hold like the previous
משנה *mishnah*. Previous משנה *mishnah*... Previous משנה *Mishnah* said הנודר מן הענבים
מותר ביין *hanoder min ha’anavim mutar beyayin* because יין *yayin* wine is
different from grapes in such an extent that it does not count
as the normal just thing that comes out of it. It's not
inside the grape. It's not that wine is inside the grape, it's
more of a process of creating wine out of grapes. רבי שמעון
בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* maybe disagrees with that משנה *mishnah*
or maybe he's just not including grapes and olives in his distinction.
Okay. According to this little chart here in this Steinsaltz, winter grapes
are exactly an example of this because it says here if you
take a נדר *neder* against winter grapes, you're actually not permitted to
eat them but you can eat the vinegar. Oh, that's interesting. So
again that was not explicit in our... well the משנה *mishnah* said
for winter grapes in general are not... right, but the way our
משנה *mishnah* said it was מאיצטבנית מותר בחומץ איצטבנית *me’itztabanit mutar bechomet
itztabanit* that it's permitted to eat the vinegar made out of them
meaning the only thing included in the נדר *neder* was... Oh, according
to רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar*. So the Steinsaltz
is saying that רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* is
disagreeing with the משנה *mishnah*. That's a good possibility as well that
he's saying no, no, no, you thought that the vinegar made from
these grapes should be permitted because you only had in mind the
grape. No, the only thing you had in mind was vinegar because
the grape itself is inedible. Okay, so that's good. Yes, though the
grapes themselves would be forbidden in the Artscroll. Oh, Artscroll has another
chart. Wait, wait, there's one opinion that winter grapes are permitted, so
then they must be edible if they... The grapes themselves are permitted?
Yeah, well, one opinion. No, because the whole point, the reason to
permit them would be דווקא *davka* because they are inedible. Inedible means
not usually eaten, right? Meaning not that it'll kill you, but it's
just that when you took the נדר *neder* against eating the winter
grapes, you meant the vinegar made from winter grapes and therefore the
grapes themselves actually would be מותר *mutar* even though the לשון *lashon*
of the נדר *neder* the word you used was referring to the
grapes themselves because you did not have intent for them at all,
you only had intent for the vinegar made from them then the
grapes themselves would be מותר *mutar*. So that would be the point
that רבי שמעון בן אלעזר *Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar* comes to make,
which is that the fruit which is itself not eaten and you
took a נדר *neder* against that fruit, the liquid that comes out
of it is prohibited but the fruit itself might remain permitted because
it's not caught in the נדר *neder* because it's not normally eaten,
you didn't even have intent for it, if you came to then
go and try to eat it it would actually be מותר *mutar*.
Let's stop here. We're halfway down נ"ג עמוד א' *nun gimmel amud
aleph*. We'll pick up there tomorrow.